<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>resume - Tag - karl</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/tags/resume/</link><description>resume - Tag - karl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://karlquinsland.com/tags/resume/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Resume</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/resume/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://karlquinsland.com/resume/</guid><description><![CDATA[<h1 id="tldr">TL;DR</h1>
<p>When asked to summarize my resume, ChatGPT said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Overall, the candidate is a highly skilled SRE with a passion for automation and optimization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When asked to expand on that further I got back a summary that was accurate and concise:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am a Senior+ level engineer with a constellation of skills in the Dev/Sec-Ops and SRE space.</p>
<p>An overall tool-smith leveraging a decade+ of cloud computing and software development experience to make both personal and professional tasks more automatic and consistent.</p>
<p>My expertise includes designing and building modern, scalable architectures as well as the CI/CD pipelines to facilitate their deployment.</p>
<p>I have also spent a decent amount of time modernizing legacy Terraform infrastructure, improving internal documentation and both developing and coaching incident management processes.</p>
<p>I believe that quality documentation is one of an engineer&rsquo;s most valuable resources.</p>
<p>I have a strong understanding of security in the application, infrastructure and organizational contexts. I have run vulnerability bounty programs and been responsible for triaging and prioritizing bounty-winning reports.</p>
<p>I am an OSS contributor with a strong background in Python and am comfortable working with a range of technologies.
I am particularly skilled at identifying opportunities for automation and building tools to streamline workflows.
I enjoy using personal time to further develop my skills and build tools to automate tasks outside of work; my personal interests and skills often overlap with my professional expertise.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="download">Download</h2>
<div class="details admonition info open">
        <div class="details-summary admonition-title">
            <i class="icon fas fa-info-circle fa-fw"></i>Note<i class="details-icon fas fa-angle-right fa-fw"></i>
        </div>
        <div class="details-content">
            <div class="admonition-content">The files linked below should be considered the most up to date copy of my recent professional roles and accomplishments.</div>
        </div>
    </div>
<ul>
<li><a href="/resume/kq.json" rel="">JSON</a> document. Complies with the <a href="https://jsonresume.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">JSON Resume</a> schema.</li>
<li><a href="/resume/kq.md" rel="">MARKDOWN</a> document which can be easily turned into HTML or PDF if you so choose.</li>
<li><a href="/resume/kq.html" rel="">HTML</a> document which can be easily turned into a PDF if you so choose.</li>
<li><a href="/resume/kq.pdf" rel="">PDF</a> document which mirrors the HTML but has most formatting stripped out for reliable machine parsing.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can also find a similar - but not identical or as current - copy of the information on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/karlq/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>