<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Electronics-Lab - Category - karl</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/categories/electronics-lab/</link><description>Electronics-Lab - Category - karl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://karlquinsland.com/categories/electronics-lab/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>electronics lab: enhanced psu</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>While doing the PoE related testing for <a href="https://karlquinsland.com/poe-at-a-distance-ruined-my-cat5-speeds/" rel="">this</a> incident, it occurred to me that I never got around to sharing the files for a small modification to the popular RD6006 PSU.</p>
<p>While drafting this post, I discovered that there appears to be a newer version of the RD6006: the 6012. As far as I can tell, they&rsquo;re in the same &lsquo;family&rsquo; and have the same dimensions so the CAD and related model files below <em>should</em> work w/ the RD6012 just as they do w/ the 6006, but i can only &lsquo;guarantee&rsquo; that the CAD and related model files below will work with the <a href="https://hackaday.com/tag/riden-rd6006/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">RD6006</a>.</p>
<p>A version of this post appears on <a href="https://www.prusaprinters.org/prints/36338-poe-and-qc30-adapter-for-rd6006-psu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">prusaprinters</a> and <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4536551" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">thingiverse</a></p>
<h2 id="what">What</h2>
<p>A small enclosure for a PoE injector and QC 3.0 charger designed to sit on top of the RD6012 PSU &lsquo;kit&rsquo; sold all over aliexpress and banggood.</p>
<p>Assembled, it looks like this:</p>
<figure >

    
        
        

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
            As seen on AliExpress
            
                
                
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>The RD6006 is incredibly versatile, but can only supply power for about 85% of the devices that make their way onto my &lsquo;healing&rsquo; bench. I wasn&rsquo;t keen on taking up more valuable space with a device dedicated to PoE injection so finding a way to mod one into the PSU seemed like a good idea. Similarly, adding a versatile USB port seemed like a no-brainer as my <a href="http://www.miniware.com.cn/product/ts80-soldering-iron-more/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">favorite soldering iron</a> is powered via QuickCharge 3.</p>
<p>Three useful bench tools, one footprint, one consumed power outlet. What&rsquo;s not to love?</p>
<h2 id="printing">Printing:</h2>
<p>There are two components for this build:</p>
<ul>
<li>the &lsquo;plate&rsquo; which rests on the top of the PSU case and has small &lsquo;fences&rsquo; to fix the circuit boards in place. It&rsquo;s the &lsquo;salmon&rsquo; colored component</li>
<li>the &rsquo;lid&rsquo; is the (mostly) transparent yellow component which holds the auxiliary power supplies (pink components) in place and keeps all voltages away from people.</li>
</ul>
<figure >

    
        
        

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <h4>Colorized Components</h4>
        
        <p>
            Relevant components, colored in F360
            
                
                
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>I used black PETG, but any material and at least 10% infill should be fine. Tune the layer height to taste.</p>
<p>The &lsquo;plate&rsquo; does not need any supports nor does the lid if printed in the suggested print orientation shown below :point_down:. I printed with settings optimized for speed so there was minimal sagging, but nothing substantial. What little there was didn&rsquo;t interfere with clearance of any other internal component and was completely hidden.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not comfortable with bridging long distances, you can optionally enforce support material from the build plate to the top of the lid <strong>or</strong> flip the lid upside down and use supports for the four feet where the screws go. Because any sagging would be hidden inside,</p>
<figure >

    
        
        

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
            suggested print orientation
            
                
                
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h2 id="components">Components</h2>
<p>In addition to the miscellaneous wire and crimp connectors, there are two components used in this design:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/33019891423.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">PoE injector</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07Y9HP4KM/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">QC 3.0 Charger</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="assembly">Assembly</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have any pictures from the assembly :disappointed:, but it&rsquo;s not particularly difficult to figure out from the attached pictures. In general, the steps to take are:</p>
<ol start="0">
<li>Print everything and clean up the parts as needed</li>
<li>de-shell the PoE injector and QC3 charger. A plastic pry-tool or a few flat-head screwdrivers will help here!</li>
<li>desolder the existing mains connections from both modules and solder on new ones. The new ones don&rsquo;t need to be long, just a bit longer than the leads that came on the module PCBs!</li>
<li>disconnect power from the assembled PSU and remove the case cover</li>
<li>place the &lsquo;plate&rsquo; onto the top of the PSU and use a pencil to mark all 5 holes on the cover</li>
<li>remove the plate, drill out all 5 holes and use a file to smooth down any sharp edges on the big hole as that&rsquo;s where the mains wires will go. A burr poking through insulation means the case may become energized @ mains voltages! :boom: :skull:</li>
<li>crimp connectors onto wires and attach to the mains supply <strong>after</strong> the switch and fuse!</li>
<li>place the &lsquo;plate&rsquo; back onto the PSU cover</li>
<li>run the wires through the new hole in the top of the PSU case and through the hole in the &lsquo;plate&rsquo;</li>
<li>add the PoE injector and QC3 module to the plate</li>
<li>join the mains leads to the module leads. I used <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Wago-221-413-LEVER-NUTS-Conductor-Connectors/dp/B06XGYXVXR/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Wago</a> connectors, but simple wirenuts or a screw terminal block will work.</li>
<li>Use M3 screws to secure the lid to the plate and the PSU. I intentionally drilled the holes slightly too small so the screws would thread against the case. Not ideal, but works absolutely fine for something that&rsquo;s not load-bearing or going to be repeatedly re-screwed.</li>
<li>re-connect the IEC power connector and power on</li>
<li>monitor for sounds and smells that indicate you screwed up. begin testing PoE and USB port for proper power.</li>
</ol>
<p>Just prior to seating the &rsquo;lid&rsquo; you should have something like this:</p>
<figure >

    
        
        

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
            components seated and wired
            
                
                
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>When all said and done, you&rsquo;ll get this:</p>
<figure >

    
        
        

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
            everything assembled and powered up
            
                
                
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h2 id="files">Files</h2>
<p>The f360 file is&hellip; a mess. I&rsquo;m not going to share it here. Contact me if you really want it. The <code>stl</code> and <code>3mf</code> files are below, though. As you can tell from the initials and date, this project was &lsquo;completed&rsquo; awhile ago.</p>
<p>For archive / posterity, all source files are included here. All files are licensed as <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike</a> (CC BY-NC-SA).</p>
<ul>
    
    <li>
        

        
        

        <figure>
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/images/modded-assembled.jpg">
                
            </a>
            
            <figcaption>
                <small>everything assembled and powered up</small>
            </figcaption>
            
        </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

        
        

        <figure>
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/images/plate_and_lid.jpg">
                
            </a>
            
            <figcaption>
                <small>Relevant components, colored in F360</small>
            </figcaption>
            
        </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        
        <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/models/combined.3mf">
            <i class="far fa-file-archive"></i>
            models/combined.3mf:
            
            <small style="font-family:'Lucida Console', monospace">3mf</small> <small>file</small>
            
            
        </a>
        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        
        <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/models/lid.stl">
            <i class="far fa-file-code"></i>
            models/lid.stl:
            
            <small style="font-family:'Lucida Console', monospace">stl</small> <small>file</small>
            
            
        </a>
        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        
        <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/models/plate.stl">
            <i class="far fa-file-code"></i>
            models/plate.stl:
            
            <small style="font-family:'Lucida Console', monospace">stl</small> <small>file</small>
            
            
        </a>
        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

        
        

        <figure>
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/images/cover-and-screws-off.jpg">
                
            </a>
            
            <figcaption>
                <small>components seated and wired</small>
            </figcaption>
            
        </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

        
        

        <figure>
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/images/print_orientation.jpg">
                
            </a>
            
            <figcaption>
                <small>suggested print orientation</small>
            </figcaption>
            
        </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

        
        

        <figure>
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/electronics-lab-enhanced-bench-psu/images/rd6012-assembled.jpg">
                
            </a>
            
            <figcaption>
                <small>As seen on AliExpress</small>
            </figcaption>
            
        </figure>

        
    </li>
    
</ul>

]]></description></item></channel></rss>