<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kubernetes - Tag - karl</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/tags/kubernetes/</link><description>Kubernetes - Tag - karl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://karlquinsland.com/tags/kubernetes/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arris SB8200 Prometheus Exporter</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/arris-sb8200-prometheus-exporter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://karlquinsland.com/arris-sb8200-prometheus-exporter/</guid><description><![CDATA[<!-- markdownlint-disable-file MD002 -->
<p>This is a very short &ldquo;announcement&rdquo; post.</p>
<p>To beef up my home-lab observability stack, I&rsquo;ve been working on a few projects to expose more data to Prometheus.
Getting metrics from my cable modem has been on the &ldquo;todo&rdquo; list for literally years.
There have been various metric exporters written in the past but they have either been archived/deleted off of GitHub or are otherwise inappropriate for my needs.
So, I wrote my own.</p>
<p>The GitHub repo is <a href="https://github.com/kquinsland/sb820_prometheus_exporter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">here</a> if you want to dive right in.</p>
<p>When set up, one possible way to visualize the data looks like this:</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        blah
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h2 id="a-few-observations">A few observations</h2>
<p>While building out the dashboard / prototyping it, a few things immediately stood out as &ldquo;interesting&rdquo;</p>
<p>After rebooting the modem, the metrics that keep track of error-corrected symbols sent/received over the connection are 0.
This makes sense as the modem has just been rebooted and hasn&rsquo;t had time to accumulate any errors yet.
The first jump in correctable/uncorrectable errors&hellip; happens to corelate directly with a meaningful change in both received/downstream power <em>and</em> transmit/upstream power.</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        blah
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>The metric exporter keeps track of how long scraping the modem&rsquo;s web interface takes as well as weather or not the scraped data was complete / well formed.
The time it takes to scrape a particular endpoint increases pretty quickly after power up before leveling off.
I&rsquo;d love to know why the web server on the modem slows down so quickly after booting up&hellip;.</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        blah
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


]]></description></item></channel></rss>