<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>recovery - Tag - karl</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/tags/recovery/</link><description>recovery - Tag - karl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://karlquinsland.com/tags/recovery/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Unbrick a rievtech PLC after failed firmware upgrade</title><link>https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>This is &ldquo;reference&rdquo; post for anybody else that happens to have this same very specific problem.</p>
<p>I was looking for a way to incorporate some of the <em>many</em> cheap / industrial grade sensors from AliExpress with Home Assistant.
Long story short: almost everything electronic in the industrial space uses <a href="https://modbus.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Modbus</a> to communicate, typically with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programmable_logic_controller" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">PLC</a>. While Home Assistant <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io/integrations/modbus/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">does have support</a> for the Modbus protocol, but wanted to use a PLC that could manage the sensors directly and expose the values over the network in a more standard format; MQTT.</p>
<p>Turns out, quite a few PLCs come with network interfaces and can speak MQTT now!</p>
<p>So I picked up a <a href="https://www.rievtech.com/PR-18DC-DAI-R-N-pd72286477.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><code>PR-18DC-DAI-R-N</code></a> PLC from the &lsquo;budget friendly&rsquo; supplier rievtech. The PLC was put into service in 2018 and never updated; the firmware version it was running was almost certainly below <code>150</code> but I didn&rsquo;t record the specific version.</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>Hoping to squash a small bug, I chose to upgrade the firmware to version <code>152</code> which was released at the end of 2020 and somehow managed to brick the device 🤦.</p>
<p>I am <em>speculating</em> but it looks like something significant changed around firmware version <code>150</code>. If you try to update a device from a version prior to <code>150</code> - like I did - something in memory is not properly migrated to the format required by versions after <code>150</code> and this causes the update process to fail before completion:</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        SO close!
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>That failure message came from the <a href="https://www.rievtech.com/phoenix/admin/download?fileId=jGUKpAvYWcQE&amp;dp=GvUApKfKKUAU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Update_Net_V152_20201205.zip</a> file which is meant for the ethernet equipped PLCs in the <code>PR</code> line. The failure apparently soft bricks the PLC.</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        Blank white screen. Non responsive buttons, Occasional blinking Ethernet lights. Fun! 🙃
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>The PLC seemed &lsquo;alive&rsquo; as I could still see <code>arp</code> packets coming from it&rsquo;s ethernet port on boot and the web server seemed to accept my connection but never return any data. Even after restarting the PLC, the firmware updater was able to open a new connection and flash the firmware&hellip; always failing at the same spot: 99.17%.</p>
<p>Clearly <em>something</em> is alive and well inside the PLC&hellip; If I can connect to whatever <em>is</em> running and convince that process to update the flash then I have a good shot to do &lsquo;solderless&rsquo; recovery. Absolute worst case, I buy another one and clone the flash memory from the working one onto the bricked one.</p>
<h2 id="recovery-process">Recovery process</h2>
<p>Turns out, their support team has a file ready to go for this exact problem! I guess I&rsquo;m not the first person. Really wish they&rsquo;d publish this file and/or procedure on their website. I could have recovered from my failure in minutes with a quick google search and saved myself a few hours of trouble shooting before drafting a support ticket&hellip; not to mention the days of waiting for a reply. Oh well. That&rsquo;s why <em>I&rsquo;m</em> documenting it.</p>
<p>I was given a 2.6MB file named <code>UpdateFail_PR-18DC-DAI-R-N_V150.zip</code>. After extracting, it looks a lot like their <em>regular</em> firmware update archives, just much smaller. I suspect that the archive is much smaller because it&rsquo;s only got flash images for a few affected models/devices. In any event, the archive comes with a <code>doc</code> file that I couldn&rsquo;t open and was able to eventually convert it to a <code>pdf</code> which is also attached to this post.</p>
<p>In short:</p>
<ul>
<li>Connect the PLC using their <a href="https://www.rievtech.com/USB-Cable-pd67130.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">programming cable</a></li>
<li>Open the COM port and &lsquo;prepare&rsquo; the device. This takes only a few seconds</li>
<li>Click the update button. In my case, I got a failure telling me to `Please power off the PLC first, and then power on again!&quot;</li>
<li>Power cycle the PLC, keeping the update program and COM port open</li>
<li>Click <code>Start</code>. The process of flashing version <code>150</code> started and took several minutes to finish</li>
</ul>
<p>This left me with a <em>completely working</em> PLC 🥳! I was able to access the web interface and use the LCD screen. I was <em>then</em> able to use the network update tool to the firmware version released recently; version <code>152</code>.</p>
<p>So there you go. If a failed network update leaves your <code>PR</code> series PLC in a mostly-not-working state, there is hope!</p>
<figure >

    
        
    

    

    <figcaption>
        
        <p>
        Able to flash Version 152 w/o issue!
        
            
        
        </p> 
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h2 id="files">Files</h2>
<ul>
    
    <li>
        
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/files/How%20to%20update%20the%20hardware.doc.pdf">
                <i class="far fa-file-doc"></i>
                files/How to update the hardware.doc.pdf:
                
                <small style="font-family:'Lucida Console', monospace">pdf</small> <small>file</small>
                
                
                <br>
                <small>sha1(How to update the hardware.doc.pdf): 0b451b11938b58c384465f5bf350b2f133848649</small>
                
            </a>
        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        
            <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/files/UpdateFail_PR-18DC-DAI-R-N_V150.zip">
                <i class="far fa-file-archive"></i>
                files/UpdateFail_PR-18DC-DAI-R-N_V150.zip:
                
                <small style="font-family:'Lucida Console', monospace">zip</small> <small>file</small>
                
                
                <br>
                <small>sha1(UpdateFail_PR-18DC-DAI-R-N_V150.zip): 60c306b521cdb15589b0e36dc73df484c2117539</small>
                
            </a>
        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

            
            
        
            <figure>
                <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/images/plc-01.jpg">
                    
                </a>
                
                <figcaption>
                    <small>Blank white screen. Non responsive buttons, Occasional blinking Ethernet lights. Fun! 🙃</small>
                </figcaption>
                
            </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

            
            
        
            <figure>
                <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/images/plc-00.jpg">
                    
                </a>
                
                
            </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

            
            
        
            <figure>
                <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/images/recovery-01.png">
                    
                </a>
                
                <figcaption>
                    <small>Able to flash Version 152 w/o issue!</small>
                </figcaption>
                
            </figure>

        
    </li>
    
    <li>
        

            
            
        
            <figure>
                <a target="_blank" href="https://karlquinsland.com/unbrick-rievtech-plc-failed-firmware-update/images/update-01.png">
                    
                </a>
                
                <figcaption>
                    <small>SO close!</small>
                </figcaption>
                
            </figure>

        
    </li>
    
</ul>

]]></description></item></channel></rss>